welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
good to go great all right hello
everyone and welcome to the stoa
i'm your host today raven and i guess
i'll do a check in
feeling a lot of thumbos energy which is
really nice it's returning
um it's really great to be here at the
starwar today to introduce
johannes for those of you who don't know
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
gather to coherent dialogue at the
knife's edge of what matters most
and the meta crisis of the meta crisis
is certainly
on the top of our minds right now and
i'm so excited to hear johannes
bring us some wisdom on this crisis that
we're all
a part of right now so johannes is a
professor of philosophy
and a heidegger scholar and the founder
of
a new guilt of philosophers an attempt
to get out of the institutions
and begin a new way of engaging with
philosophy
a return to maybe the old way and he's
going to share with us
some words of wisdom and with that
johannes i'll pass it over to you
thank you very much raven thank you very
much peter
um i maybe briefly
how this was born probably out of a joke
uh because i said in the video
what's next the meta crisis of the
mental crisis
and then peter commented the metacrisis
of the metacrisis
lol um and
but let's just say peter we've memed it
into existence perhaps maybe that's
appropriate to put it like that but
maybe there's something else really
that's going on here i did not
i didn't say it just just to be
provocative uh or awful
um even though i'm quite you know i have
a tendency to be like that a bit
sometimes perhaps
but i think that what the meta crisis
or the this course let's just say around
the metacrisis get set
is that there is in fact a profound
crisis that's occurring um however i
found that the discourse around it will
probably lead to an infinite regress
to say it bluntly it's because i think
that
any kind of
any kind of problem solving will not do
um the task lies somewhere else
so i wrote this piece now over the past
week because last week i saw something
popping up on twitter and i said
uh the meta crisis of the meta crisis is
here
um and i'll now get into it i think it's
it's got it's
it's a i'm trying to say too much in
too little time it's not properly
developed yet
but it's a first attempt perhaps and i
begin with the word
crisis and then i move into descartes
and then on to
um to can't
and yeah so i hope it's
uh i hope it it's clear what i'm trying
to say maybe it's not even clear to me
but we'll find out so the meta crisis of
the meta crisis
perhaps it is helpful to begin
with the meaning and the origin of the
word
crisis and what its concept signifies
for us today
if we begin to take seriously that
apparently something announces itself in
the ubiquity of
crisis perhaps it would even be fair to
claim that crisis
and its specific dimension is today that
which addresses us
most urgently and assuming this is
indeed the case the question perhaps
becomes
when's this utmost urgent
crisis the word crisis is of course
of ancient greek origin what else
the greek greece's means separation
dichotomy conflict strife
but also selection and decision
hippocrates speaks of crisis
also as pertaining to disease creases
here means the moment
when the fate of the patient is decided
either for recovery or for death in
tragedy
cases is the singular incision or the
moment when the hero's destiny becomes
apparent
according to the brother scrim
dictionaries
dictionary of the german language good
writes somewhere
all transitions are crisis
and is a crisis not a disease so that's
the quote from goods we could then
perhaps translate or maybe cross
over as i'd like to think of it from the
shore of the greeks to ours
ferry across the river of the eons the
word creases as
follows the within itself turning
of self-conflicting strife thanks to
which selection and decision transpire
so that the path entered upon
irreversibly becomes one's own
and this entering upon the path however
is the instance in which crisis
disappears a crisis appears when a
transition is paving its way for itself
another grounding needs to be prepared
and this seems to be coming from
behind as it were barely seen rather
than looming on the horizon
it is in the paving for itself that the
path
this indicates that this also requires
a decision and once the crisis is
brought into focus
the word decision pleases the modern ear
it would seem from making decisions as
the english vernacular says
indicates that something can be done
control can be executed
the crisis can and hence should be
managed
to minimize damage or in suffering
perhaps
and maximize utility and still
despite the will to make decisions and
control
there seems to be crisis over crisis the
climate crisis
the corona crisis the financial economic
social political institutional
intersubjective crisis
there is a housing crisis homelessness
crisis a public health crisis
a mental health crisis crisis
upon crisis that recur every year
almost some of them diseases upon
diseases
when we follow gertie yet
the question is is anything ever truly
decided
bearing in mind that to decide means to
cut
off from latin to cut it may well be
that
all those crises are not at all to be
solved there is no decision to be found
instead those crises are what the
all-willing subject perhaps
clings to as this pun crisis
is now what gives the subject absolute
self-certainty
maybe it's in the crisis i'm trying to
say
that we still find something to hold on
to
as long as everything is in utter crisis
i
can and must and will manage the
pandemic
crisis i can even engage in abstract
meta games of crisis that are entirely
it seems detached from anything and
purely in the realm
of constructivism hence
without the suffering experience of the
painful cut
which comes necessarily with any disease
and any transition
it is as though high from the balcony
view
some stand comfortably overlooking the
world
pressed into the procrastination of
models and representations
a blueprint of the meta crisis which so
the assumption goes only needs
all the right conditions met a priori
before any experience
for the so-called meza and meeting
crisis to be easily
and maybe even comfortably overcome
just take the ingredients of some
rationality and
causality don't forget the spiritual
though
and here is your entertaining
epidermally interesting to quote
nietzsche a neatly defined
set of delusions solutions and maybe
delusions to
but i mean solutions here abstractly
applicable
to the meta crisis the historicized
sterility
with which thinking is approached
indicates that something has broken off
and has gone astray the philosophy is no
longer in charge
of what is of what it has always been in
charge of
namely the grounding and founding of
world axis
alas what is seemingly becoming ever
clearer is that
modernity itself is crisis that is the
grand claim of this humble essay
the attempt to solve problems in the
cold and distanced
way proposed to solve even thinking
itself
indicate to me a misunderstanding of the
task of thinking
thinking does not require solving or
correct solutions
thinking needs to be thought now how is
one to make sense of this grandiose
remark
that all modernity is crisis
the epoch which gives itself the name
modernity
of the present moment is what it means
begins with descartes
this is not intended to give a precise
date or year
but a transition perhaps an incision
which the name of descartes now stands
for
is indicated here hegel says on the
meaning of descartes and i quote from
his
history of philosophy this is hegel it
is only now with descartes that we
properly arrive at the philosophy of the
new
world after a long time
airing across the sea hegel continues it
is with descartes that philosophy
finally begins to see land again for it
is with descartes
says hegel that philosophy begins to
appreciate
the importance of consciousness
for truth of the eye of the ego
descartes doubts and khan's contribution
khan's contributions
i would have given birth
to the modern world more than anything
from anyone else
the oft-cited so-called cartesian
paradigm
has become the unquestioned boogeyman
at this point which can be pulled out
the magician's head at any moment
a conversation requires a quick and easy
deus ex machina
to find someone or something to blame
nothing of what is being said here
intends to blame
descartes or anyone in fact the
unquestioned repeated talk of the
cartesian paradigm
the confusion subject is perhaps a
rather
thoughtless operation precisely because
it neglects the necessity of the thought
of descartes
and what he responded to
why is it that the soul becomes the
reis kogitans the thinking thing which
in turn becomes the ground for
philosophy
why is it that casting doubt
methodologically
and that is to say the negation of all
certainty in order to arrive at absolute
certainty
is at the heart of his thinking why
is it that mental perception begins to
take the upper hand how
is it that the human being becomes the
subject
the ground of objectivity circling
around and within itself but at the same
time establishing
not only self-certainty but also again
certainty over the objective world
why had it become necessary to establish
and this is the most important question
why
had it become necessary to establish
this certainty over the objective world
which is not just one of control
but also secures that which philosophy
has always assumed
the unity of being and thought
it is only when this unity breaks away
when it collapses that the subject is
truly
trapped within itself perhaps what
descartes responded to
with his methodological doubt is what we
can call
the pandemonic crisis that is modernity
namely the split
between the unity of being and thought
perhaps this had already announced
itself to him perhaps
already an utter withdrawal was he found
the a priori which descartes finds in
the race
kogitans the thing that thinks of itself
without negating itself but everything
else
should itself instill this quiet and
unease within us still descartes
is an exercise of freedom for his
thinking attempts to begin anew
and it casts doubt on everything and
takes a distinct stance
in the midst of beings there is a
tremendous philosophical autonomy in
descartes
thanks to its negativity yet at once
this skeptical negation
of the world it neglects
uh for it neglects the negativity of the
subject sets in motion
the self positing of the subject
and the this freedom though should be
taken seriously
and also should be honored while bearing
in mind that
here also the isolation of the human
being subject sets
in insofar as everything is doubted and
negated but not
the self the self is transformed
into a thinking thing a substance of
sorts
the being of this thinking thing knows
no negativity however
still the audacity to cast out on
everything to negate the existence of
all that is but still to say i think i
am
is an exercise in testimony of
tremendous human freedom and as such
is at the heart of what modernity is at
the same time
the self-referential ego as cochitans
becomes the grounded ground the
foundation
in which the human being finds a stance
this foundation as we can see
now neglects however the world and
depicts a raiification of the self
a self which is now isolated
even though i think that descartes tried
to establish again the unity between
being and thought with descartes there
is an onset
a new beginning as it were there is also
a necessity to it and so far as thinking
always begins
when it removes itself from tradition
and dogma
at the same time thinking must however
also
take into care and heat tradition or
rather
that which is being delivered over for
in that which
has been the eternal strength of
a new beginning always sways
the distinct negativity of modernity is
hence
one's one which doubts and denies what
came before
and at once forgets the negativity of
being
it's a double negation that doesn't know
of its own negation of
the negation this is how you get to the
importance of spinoza and hegel of the
that every determination is negation
with to the double negation of
of of hegel the neglected negativity of
modernity
transpires as critique or with nietzsche
as the spirit of resentment
nietzsche's saratoustra says not only
the reason of millennia but also its
madness is breaking out within us
what i have elsewhere referred to as the
apocalypse of the subject
seems to be just this the
total exhaustion of the will to
eradicate negativity
which forgets its own annihilating force
pushing against
its utmost limit and simultaneously the
slow realization that the withdrawal
cannot be stopped all the while in the
withdrawal i mean
off of the unity of being and thought
all the while dancing along liminal
digital virtual a liminal digital
virtual edge
established by the plethora of
historicized
files of meaning particles to which the
late modern subject
clings if only for a split second for
the subject is trying to arrive
back at the certainty of the unity
between being
and thought and this unity finally
collapsed
with hume's radical skepticism
hume awakened kant from his dogmatic
slumbers not least because of the
former's
own fundamental dogmatic skepticism
the dogmatism of which can't speak so is
the presupposed
unity of being and thought a
presupposition
which now needs to be cashed and needs
to be shown
that this synthetic a priori judgment is
in fact
valid the critical project of kant is to
bring to the fore
this foundational presupposition of
which thought had dogmatic
which thought had dogmatically assumed
for itself khan does not do so
does do so not in order to tear down the
metaphysical presupposition but to place
it on firm grounds
so that the unity of being and thought
can be secured and saved
the transcendental deduction hence does
not deduce but
wants to justify the usage of the
categories and the concepts of the
subject
kant is an auf clere an enlightenment
philosopher
precisely because he clarifies clears up
discloses this fundamental
presupposition and at once
sees the perfect ethical duty to himself
and humanity
to establish again a possibility for the
human being to access the world
and trust the access to the world
because the other solution is skepticism
or nihilism skepticism nihilism were
basically the same meaning
around that time establishing how we
access and approach the world has always
been the mandate of philosophy even if
contemporary
academia perhaps has forgotten that and
only looks at the so-called history of
philosophy
as some alienated distant object even
though kant clarifies for us
that thinking must necessarily make this
presupposition which is an a priori
synthetic judgment for kant
in order to get back out into the world
that is in order to establish the unity
of being in thought again
where thought is understood as
representation for khan the objectivity
of object
is now predicated on the subjectivity of
the subject
that means on its categories with can't
what we have access to are
representations of appearances but never
things as they are in themselves
and um just to say this briefly the on
the path to
victor schelling and hegel salomon
maymon is extremely important
to because he marries khan's critical
project with with dogmatic metaphysics
and says we do
recognize things in themselves through
through their appearances
to which we have access but he still
ends up in skepticism
why because he denies the
possibility of negativity he doesn't see
that every
positing every position also has its own
negation
with it so this denial of negativity or
this denial of death on some other level
um always leads to a skepticism or
nihilism now the um
with khan what we have access to are
representations of appearances but not
things as they are in themselves
things as they are in themselves are
pushed into the
nameless realm the no women on the
nominal nomenon means no name
again kant still needs to establish
the unity of being and thought once more
and he does it
with this move or else the specter of
skepticism and nihilism which comes
through with hume and others would begin
to take hold
and the human being would find no stance
and no access to the world
at the same time khan's and his attempt
to secure this access to the world and
the unity of being and thought
cunt also establishes however
a nearly fictitious phenomenal world
that is to say now with khan all we seem
to have
access to are representations of
appearances
quite close to an illusion the crisis
then
that the first critique brings to the
fore on multiple levels
is the genuine metacrisis of modernity
namely the sudden disappearance of the
unity of being and thought
about which modernity enlightens us
in the first place and through this
enlightenment the various attempts to
establish some unity again
almost to heal the dichotomy between
human being and world
the establishment of an illusory field
of perception however with kant
is necessary and victor schelling and
hegel will try to overcome this
in their own ways i would say 50
shelling jose
heidegger paul naitorp um are all
attempts
in heidegger of course too with thought
with the transcendental philosophy of
darzan
are all attempts to struggle against
subjectivism
and to overcome it i would like to say
it again thanks to kant and hume and
others
we see the dogmatism of traditional
metaphysics the dogmatic presupposition
yet at once what is torn open here
and the terrible wound that it
disinflicts is the bursting
away of the human from a an
access to the genuine world as to to
things as they are in themselves
you read heidige for example you read
the passages on
the short essay the thing begins on the
question what is the thing in itself
precisely for that reason it is crucial
to point out that it is with kant and
only with his transcendental logic
that the natural sciences find
justification for their constructions of
objects without inherent contradictions
so what the scientists do in their
models is that they
construct objects without contradictions
and this is the
earthquake we name can't the attempt
though
must not be to solve i think must not be
to solve
abstractly in a priori this profound
crisis
but to think it through
to let its own overturning
occur i would like to
quote from kant from the very first
two paragraphs of the first edition of
his first critique because i think it's
quite telling
khan says the following human reason has
the peculiar fate
in one species of its cognitions that it
is burned with questions which it cannot
dismiss
since they are given to it as problems
by the nature of reason itself
but which it also cannot answer since
they transcend
every capacity of human reason reason
falls into this perplexity through no
fault of its own
it begins from principles whose use is
unavoidable in the course of experience
and at the same time sufficiently
warranted by it
with these principles it rises as its
nature also requires ever higher
to more remote conditions but since it
becomes aware
in this way that its business must
always remain incomplete
because the questions never cease reason
sees itself necessitated to take refuge
and principles
that overstep all possible use and
experience
and yet seems so unsuspicious that even
ordinary common sense agrees with them
but it thereby falls into obscurity and
contradictions
from which it can indeed surmise that it
must somewhere be proceeding on the
ground of hidden
errors but it cannot discover them
for the principles on which it is
proceeding since they surpass
the bounds of all experience no longer
recognize
any touchstone of experience the
battlefield
of these endless controversies is called
metaphysics
we are then it seems addressed by
something
and hence we are to respond again
not by solving in a calculative manner
the problems
at hand a priori but by thinking through
what is at stake
whether and how being and thinking can
still belong together
so that this utmost crisis becomes the
following
something that from within itself
overturns itself
the meta crisis of the meta crisis
this course could then be summarized as
follows
the sudden insight into the
groundlessness of the attempts to solve
abstractly and a priori all presently
available concrete problems
constructing a world without
contradictions
the dead formal logic of the various
problems solving attempts
attempt to construct the perfect world
without contradictions which inevitably
will lead
to inherent contradictions to antinomies
of reason
is kant himself admits in
the first critique all the while
failing to understand that thinking does
not require solutions
that the mandate of thinking is now to
bring
together again to reconcile the fissure
between being and thinking humans and
earth
gods and mortals perhaps from the deep
shared memory of the all
unifying one thank you very much
wow thank you
rich oh my gosh there's so many things
here
okay so for any everybody in the
audience if you have any questions or
statements or points of clarification
that you would like to address to
johannes you can go ahead and put those
in the chat
and then i will call your name and you
can mute yourself and ask your question
directly to johannes
and i have to kind of let's
there's a couple things that you brought
up yeah
i think i'd like some clarification on
there seems to be this
this theme of contradiction
and then earlier you said double
negation
the double negation um of modernity
could you go back
and clarify what that means
um okay i think what i
said and this wasn't written um
so what i what i think i said is that it
it negates negativity right so in that
sense it's it's some kind of a double
negation
the the the the program of
um um of of modernity is to
get rid of negativity now if you take
this
to a logical level that means to negate
negativity but that
so if you want what you if you want to
get rid of negativity you have to negate
it what is that but how do you negate
it what do you get
sorry how do you get rid of
what does it mean to get rid of
negativity
we have to ask the modernists um it's
it's
this is one of the programmatic um
lines in in in modernity one of the main
trajectories
is to be able to pause it i mean it's
it's most proclaimed for example in the
movement called positivism
which the positivity
means to have a world that's
purely positive that's that we can that
we can
manifest and control um without any
negativity negativity on our level of
course
is is death is finitude etc um
but the program of one of the main i
think
trajectories of modernity is trying to
rid ourselves
from for example just stay with death
from death
um it's now a major problem
just a prolonging of life for example is
an attempt to get rid of
the negativity of death or negativity or
finitude
um so it's it's on extremely many levels
that you can find this attempt to get
rid of
the negative but at all the while it's
neglecting
uh its own sort of inherent negativity
and it runs i'm started reading um
salomon maymon who is the the so
who's the bridge between khan and victor
and shelling
and hegel um and even he has to admit
that they're
every that there must be some kind of
negation they'll be positing
so spinoza is is an early case
an early modern philosophy who
understands that every determine
one of his quote omnis determination is
negative right
you you cannot determine anything
without negation
hegel will radicalize this further and
say yeah the the proper self-autonomy is
the negation of the negation
and but this is a conscious if you like
this is a quantity this is a negation
that's aware of itself
right a negation is not aware of itself
um loses itself in negation here's the
strange thing the more that's positive
the more lost there is
um along the line it's
a world that's positive becomes
artificial
okay yes that makes that it's beginning
to make sense
and so so uh okay so we have this
negation and we have the uh
the forgetting of the double negation in
modernity is that kind of what you're
saying
it's uh and then there's the conscious
uh
negation is that related to
contradiction are those there's a
distinction between contradiction and
asian okay yeah verify that
um well the the
the a purely positive philosophy or
positive way of thinking
must negate negation but also
contradiction so it must construct
um
so it must construct uh the it must
construct for example objects without
inherent contradiction
but um in in order to say that uh
i don't know this this pen is this pen
properly in an interrelationality it
must be
not this book uh if i run into extreme
troubles to
to be able to try and determine what
this pen is
if i can't say what it isn't it's the
same with with myself right this is
the i mentioned the it's the freedom of
descartes the the audacity is
to say all of this isn't i think i
am is there is is the response um but
that's exactly
right it he comes back to himself he
comes back to
his thinking and of course logically not
not personally
um and i think the the the there is a
difference between
negation and contradiction um
which perhaps we could say is
um
a contradiction works by
um a contradiction works by negation but
isn't
just uh kind of cannot be reduced to
negation
absolutely a contradiction must be there
must already be i think bit more
uh at work if that makes sense and the
um the the reason why
why so can't it finds this i mean what's
so
i should have probably said a lot more
about khan than your stuff
um because someone just asked what's the
matter crisis of the meta crisis
i think the the crisis that we're facing
really
is this splits or this collapse between
the unity of being
and thought which is which can be you
can
this sounds very abstract but this can
be for example the question is there
even an external world or am i just
trapped within myself
um or is is the split between
the human and the natural world which to
some degree always is necessary but it
always must also come back
to it right but a purely sort of a
purely positivistic world
cannot use this kind of it cannot think
contradiction
so to think contradiction you have to
also think negation i have to be able to
negate my animality in order to become
human to speak with hegel
and in so becoming you are not totally
denying my natural
body or world or animality
i'm actually affirming it through the
negation but then i have to be able to
think
uh contradiction i have to be able to
accept that there are
contradictions that actually thinking in
spirit moves by
negativity and then hence by
contradiction
um it it's there's a movement in there
it's all alive
one of the things you you learn when you
read hegel is that logic is something
that's living and breathing
the difference with formal logic is that
formal logic is dead
it doesn't allow for it it crowds out
natural language
it has to formalize everything it's all
a priori without
experience um and then reapplies itself
to
so it's non-ontological strangely enough
fragi for example
anti-ontological what is now i think
what we're now witnessing
is that it's now re-ontologizing and
then making
judgments about the natural world
through models etc
um and the so
i'm not sure if this makes it clearer um
but
kind of the there is there's a
a connection between uh contradicting
and negating and so far as you uh negate
you're already on the movement towards
contradicting
um but you're kind of you're you're
you're bringing it all
in right and if you allow for a double
indication so by bike sick
being aware of it and allowing for it
um it you're not solving the problem of
contradiction
but it becomes um a living hole
if that makes sense yeah
yeah uh rain do you want to follow up
with your question at all
yeah sure um maybe i'll follow up
because that was helpful
i feel like i'm getting a better
understanding well i'm trying to
but yeah i understand yeah i'm not a
philosopher um but i like
risk thought um so
was actually the question that's coming
up for me right now is
if um construction
i'm going to phrase things this way if
construction is the negation of
um sort of like this primordial nature
things as they are undifferentiated
um then then the negation of the
negation
would be the deconstruction
of of that modernist creation
so um you may disagree with that
isomorphism but do you equate
deconstruction with the double negation
or
where would you fit in deconstruction or
or a meta modernist reconstruction
yeah okay i think um i i answered to um
to adam it's a month ago or so
on twitter when it comes to that so i'm
not well well steeped
in uh in davida
and others but i think so
look looking at it from from maybe where
i'm coming from what what
what what this gets at um is
to a certain degree um
trying to um
deconstruct the overly uh
constructivistic
approach to say existence the world
right that's i think what they're trying
to do and at the same
time um it's so that's that's the
negation of course the trouble is you
you must also
you must not one i think one shouldn't
stop it just
deconstructing because then you're left
with with nothing
i mean you're just left with nothing and
it gets a bit
troublesome um but but the i think the
approach was
uh in that sense uh justified to try
to try and get back from this overly
a cold dead formally rationalistic way
of being in the world yes
that's how i i've always understood it
at least
all right let's see here so we have
stephen and then adam also has a
question
so let's see what stephen has to say and
then we'll go to adam
stephen would you like to meet yourself
and ask a question
hi my camera's playing up i can turn it
on actually it's just it's not very
pleasant to look at
uh there we go um my question i mean
i just sort of bring very blunt and i'm
trying to ground things
um and just come at it sort of bluntly
the question is would it be fair to say
the loss of the war generation
who enforced wisdom traditions albeit
dogmatically
has left a meta vacuum and this is what
we're uh
this is this is i don't know if it feels
very crass it's but
it feels like this is what we're
wrestling with it's a very empiricist
question
coming from from someone of the the
proud british
imperialist tradition i know steve quite
well so i can say this to him
um so uh
um i i can't say anything to that
because i'm not a historian
right i said
this could be you know but but then
again you would have to
wonder i mean me so this is going to be
very weird as a response to this
question
nietzsche says somewhere that it could
be that all of europe can be
kept in 30 books it doesn't need anyone
it just needs the books
and to some degree that's true when you
look at the period of the middle ages
and then the resurfacing of of aristotle
in plato and others
and the renaissance movement um so it's
i think the the question here is less
uh empirical but more really on the
level of
of of this split um
and the split is it it's this and this
is the
this weird double movement so descartes
must find a something to hold on to
and that and that means to secure some
kind of
control over the unity of being and
thought which could just be
subject over object but at the same time
this also opens up the troublesome
trajectory of the dichotomy of
human being and natural world let's say
to make it a bit more accessible
and conten is an enlightener an
enlightenment philosopher
not because he runs around and tells
everyone what to do no because he's
enlightening us about this dogmatic
presupposition that thinking had always
made
and this is the enlightenment sort of uh
this is the the achievement but then at
the same time
this leads to the trouble even more so
than with
descartes that we no longer have access
to
things as they are in themselves this is
sounds so benign but
when you say we don't have access to
things as they are
in themselves then we don't have access
to anything
real right we
we're only dealing with we're dealing
with appearances
and here's the weirdest thing it's
transcendental logic
by which we fly airplanes um we can fly
airplanes because we can
paradigmatically
set a priori that the kerosene and this
is just a positive
will react the same way over and over
and over again
i know this is very peskyly continental
in german
but um i apologized
he suffered through so many seminars
with me um
okay so it's it's this split right
uh this this extreme split and but
here's
here's the wonderful thing because maybe
this question maybe i can turn around
and make it less painful for everyone
even though there are unfortunately
always again these tremendous losses
with wall of
entire generations not not entire
generations but many of a generation
dying
and a lot is lost there is something
that we are
attuned to from which we
can still find meaning it does
need only a few texts and it does need
only a bit of awakening right there is
something to an amnesia
there is something to
name it to memory in this regard
but maybe i'm just saying it again what
i think is going on i think that this
split and collapse of this trusting
relationship between
human and world being in thought that's
what's at stake
and what we now if there's anything that
we should do
then we shouldn't try and solve this we
should try and
think the coming together of being in
thought
and this can take many different forms
right this can be
uh this can be it can be very you know
localism is one way of dealing with it
politically etc
um but on this other level and here's
here's the other strange thing about
philosophy philosophy is the
way that or is the method or i don't
know what it is actually but
i don't know method the way in which
uh the thinking through which we find
access to the world and i think this is
also why there is now
this increased interest
in philosophy and this openness to
listen to weirdos like me on the
internet
but who else
let's hear from adam yes good to meet
you finally adam
hi johannes can you hear me yes sir
yeah good um
thanks thanks for this um i mentioned to
you already that i'm
quite happy you're doing this even if
it seems like i'm just reading the
comments in the chat and
um appreciating that if if this is new
territory that it can
it can sound a bit arcane and and
difficult and
what's the point of all of this but um i
really do think that
this is the context that you're the the
the context you're speaking to johannes
is
is the context that the meta crisis
needs to be understood within um and i
think
a lot of what you're setting up
is has has become so deeply sedimented
into how we think and approach the world
that some of those assumptions and and
suppositions
um maybe don't show up for people um
as part of the problem um
you just think about how casually the
assumption of subjectivism is so
casually inserted
into almost almost every mode of
thinking
and that's exactly the problem that that
you're you're raising and
um so i think you know okay so we have
descartes we have hume we have con we
have
you know all of these different sort of
um i think of them as sort of like
dethroners decenterers
uh critical philosophers who who make
this break
with thought and being and then
the task now is to to rethink in light
of that
critical insight without without
retreating prior to kant
again to think that relation of
thought and being with kant or after
kant or something like that it's
taking kant seriously in that discussion
and so
i'm wondering with the setup
that you have here that i that i uh
agree with
um where do you where do you
where does your thinking then go like if
this is the
if this is sort of the problematic if
this is sort of the dynamic that we're
faced with i have some thoughts on it um
it's very much
what i'm trying to understand and trying
to think and trying to put into words
which i think is a whole other um
category here
um and for me i appeal to things like
like like older concepts like like
mataxi like the in-between
or like a kind of platonic participation
or when people talk about descartes and
kant they'll sometimes talk about a turn
to the subject
right philosophy enters this mode of
turning to the subject instead of trying
to
assert metaphysically what is the case
about the world
they turn to the subject to try to
understand how does the subject's
constructive faculties
uh deliver the world that we see the
world of appearances that we see
but that was an epistemological turn
mostly it's couched in epistemological
terms and i hear
people today saying yes the turn to the
subject was important but maybe we can
do
maybe we can turn to the subject in a
metaphysical way
maybe we can understand the metaphysics
of the subject
as something like um
an outgrowth of the world that it is
trying to describe
an outgrowth of in other words the
kantian categories are
emergent phenomena of of a kind of a
numeral realm that it may not know fully
but it is nevertheless a product of um
and so i
i'm just these are kind of like the
loose thoughts i have
when trying to think thought and being
again
now um and i'm wondering like what do
you think about that
where where does your thinking go now
that you've set this up
um yeah that's that's the
you know that's the crux of the meta
it's um
i think we so what
we i think what we cannot do is we
cannot brush aside
modernity so we cannot say well
descartes got it wrong obviously
because there is something to the eye to
the ego
that's important um that we must
understand um one of the
one of the responses to this entire
problem
i think the greatest one so far is
probably hegel's
with the establishing of the um
identity of non-identity
so that there is because someone just
brought it up subject object
is inseparable and that's exactly right
for hegel
you know i i am and so far i am not this
table but i am also this table
to some degree i mean this is weird to
say this but it
you are what you are by not
being something else but you are still
related to everything else by not
being everything else this is how you
become an individual heidegger's way of
thinking is
another with the i think um
what you can see with with hustle for
example is that
back to the things for example i think
to see the translations exactly the same
question right
we need to get access again to
to things as they really are to being
and not so because you brought up my
taxes methexis means participation
participation of what
of the particular in the universal so it
means that that the tree in front of me
for plato is it really is it is a tree
insofar as it participates
in treeness um
and in which we're trying to to
construct worlds that are like that
right even just in everyday language you
can hear it but it's strange also when
when adam brought up subjectivism
um listen to language there might be
some german speakers here
uh there's at least one more besides me
um when you listen to german speaking
it's
german vernacular uses the word forced
in vernacular the entire time
foreshadowing means representation idea
it's my thought so the first sentence of
schopenhauer's world as will and
representation is the world is my
representation and that rings
true for uh this is you know you can
it's not solipsistic for schopenhauer
but it has become the solipsism now
where it's it's just
my representation and the representation
is just a mental image at this point too
it has no more access to something
that's out there
it's no it's not really a regulative
idea either it's it's
trapped in in in the mind right
so my thinking would be i think where
i'm going
um is a
a bit of an idiosyncratic thinking
together of
of hegel and and heidegger
because i think what what i didn't
actually i did say at the end hen panta
anai or i said the all unifying one
um the this is a quote from
from heraclitus i think especially with
what what's happening in
the globalized world we're looking at
each other there's people in
wherever you all of you are um there is
a unification also occurring at the same
time
right so i think what we have to be able
to appreciate is this understanding that
yes
one is many but how do we think this
oneness and how do we think
the many in the one um i think that's
important that's where i'm going with
this and also so it would be as kind of
a strange
combination of of heidegger and hegel in
the sense that
i want to understand um opposites no
longer
dialectically but as belonging together
and i find also in hiding as being
notion of
being in the world not a solution but a
way of
of of to pushing the human being back
out
into the world and this is
this is why my thesis was on death
basically i think really it comes down
to appreciating again death
negativity finitude non-availability and
non-control
ability too which is something for
occidental human beings for the for
westerners
is extremely difficult to understand
especially after
in in modernity we
it's it lies if you want to have it you
know practically
it lies in the art of letting go
yeah a bit of a convoluted answer but it
was a very good question
the question was better than the answer
i would say
adam do you have any follow-up
um i do but
it's uh i don't i i feel like we could
turn this into a whole other
event and discussion so i think yeah i
think we should we should have that
conversation but um
i'll i'll leave it to other folks so
that we don't
suck all the air out of the room yeah
well we're wrapping we're coming to
the the end of the hour and i'm also
feeling that energy that there's a lot
more that we could
dig into here and we've got contrarians
in the room as well so
we can always continue this uh in some
other form i mean
because you mentioned the beginning you
know this is something i forgot to say
that i thought i would say of course i
forgot uh is you are kind of building
um something that's very important for
philosophy which is an institution
outside the
official institution um so
you know one talk with one couple of
good questions should lead to the next
one
um because now i will have to go back
over this
and rewrite a few things uh make a few
things perhaps clearer
um and then give it again okay hold it
again or put it on my channel whatever
happens
um and then we we continue one of the
things that we could do for example is a
bit of a
sort of a podium discussion perhaps also
we become prepared
with two short talks or three um
and then a longer discussion we planned
for a bit more
maybe two hours or so then all in
i think that's an excellent idea yeah i
feel like an hour for
dense philosophy is just this is not
sufficient
i'm always going over time with my
seminar i know you are we're always
hanging out for like two hours
plus it's great well
we are at the top of the hour johannes
thank you so much for
bringing us this rich cute
thanks for watching yes of course and
thanks all
lovers and haters i'll see you next time
and with that peter would uh would you
like to close out with events
yes yeah johannes thank you again for
for coming to the stoa
uh if you want to send me this the um
the transcript of
that talk i can post it on the youtube
video i'll probably do it tomorrow
you can do a post on your channel too
and then we can kind of figure out how
to do another collaboration after that
um yeah we have a bunch of upcoming
events we're going to get kicked out of
the zoom room quite
soon because there's a social design
club with the human systems people
that is at 1 30 pm eastern time
what else do we have today tyson are you
still in this
room if you're going to mute yourself
and tell us about your event that you
have
coming up sure thank you michael mead
will be here today at three o'clock
eastern
he is a mythologist a storyteller and an
author
and he'll be bringing in a mythic
perspective
around collective rites of passage
collective initiation
and how that relates to our personal
genius
and how we um explore that in communitas
so bringing in that storyteller element
i look forward to it and i'd love to see
you there
thank you tyson travis is your event
back on this week
it is yes so we'll be doing breaking the
frame
tonight at uh at 7 30 pm
and we're just gonna tinker with our
deeply held world views
and look at those and uh
right before that at 6 pm eastern time
we have the dangerous space do you know
how to always talk about safe spaces we
have a dangerous space where we talk
about
dangerous ideas and that's with ariel
friedman and that's at 6 pm eastern time
our speed of that the still is based off
a gift economy
you go to the website and if you we have
all these illustrations of our
facilitators if you go to the one that
looks like a filipino woman
that's actually raven uh you can gift to
her directly
because she does an excellent job at
emceeing these events so uh thank you
everyone for
coming out today
thank you again